# Jake Brawer, Ph.D.

Ph.D. in Computer Science / website / github / jake.brawer@yale.edu

#### Research overview

#### Summary

I build human-robot collaborative systems that learn through their interactions. My research draws upon recent innovations in machine learning as well as foundational techniques in artificial intelligence for designing systems that learn and utilize abstract knowledge to make social and physical interactions more naturalistic and robust.

#### **EDUCATION**

2016-2023	Ph.D. in Computer Science Yale University, Advisor: Brian Scassellati
2012-2016	B.A. in Cognitive Science: Computer Science minor Vassar College

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# 2016-Current Robotics Ph.D. student –Social robotics laboratory, Yale University Human–robot collaboration research under the supervision of Professor Brian Scas-

sellati.

2014-2015 **Research Fellow** –Interdisciplinary robotics research lab, *Vassar College*Designed and programmed a genotype-phenotype mapping scheme for mobile behavior-based robots incorporating sexual reproduction and ontogenetic factors.

## IN PROGRESS

Qin, Meiying, Brawer, Jake, and Scassellati, Brian (2023). "Using Task, Affordance, and Motion Planning (TAAMP) to Detect Infeasible or Limited Solutions in Affordance-Constrained Environments". In: In submission at the 2023 IEEE international conference on robotics and automation (ICRA). IEEE.

# JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Qin, Meiying, **Brawer**, **Jake**, and Scassellati, Brian (2022a). "Robot Tool Use: A Survey". In: Frontiers in Robotics and AI 9, p. 369.
- \* Qin, Meiying, \* Brawer, Jake, and Scassellati, Brian (2021). "Rapidly Learning Generalizable and Robot-Agnostic Tool-Use Skills for a Wide Range of Tasks". In: Frontiers in Robotics and AI 8, p. 380.

Brawer, Jake, Hill, Aaron, Livingston, Ken, Aaron, Eric, Bongard, Joshua, and Long Jr, John H (2017). "Epigenetic Operators and the Evolution of Physically Embodied Robots". In: Frontiers in Robotics and AI 4, p. 1.

\* Authors contributed equally

#### Conference proceedings

- Brawer, Jake, Ghose, Debasmita, Candon, Kate, Qin, Meiying, Roncone, Alessandro, Vazquez, Marynel, and Scassellati, Brian (2023). "Interactive Policy Shaping for Human-Robot Collaboration with Transparent Matrix Overlays". In: Proceedings of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction. IEEE.
- Qin, Meiying, Brawer, Jake, and Scassellati, Brian (2022b). "Task-Oriented Robot-to-Human Handovers in Collaborative Tool-Use Tasks". In: 2022 31st IEEE International Conference on Robot & Human Interactive Communication (RO-MAN). IEEE.
- Brawer, Jake, Qin, Meiying, and Scassellati, Brian (2020). "A causal approach to tool affordance learning". In: 2020 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE, pp. 8394–8399.
- Brawer, Jake, Mangin, Olivier, Roncone, Alessandro, Widder, Sarah, and Scassellati, Brian (2018). "Situated Human–Robot Collaboration: predicting intent from grounded natural language". In: *Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*.
- Scassellati, Brian, **Brawer**, **Jake**, Tsui, Katherine, Nasihati Gilani, Setareh, Malzkuhn, Melissa, Manini, Barbara, Stone, Adam, Kartheiser, Geo, Merla, Arcangelo, Shapiro, Ari, et al. (2018). "**Teaching Language to Deaf Infants with a Robot and a Virtual Human**". In: *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. ACM, p. 553.
- Tan, Zong Xuan, Brawer, Jake, and Scassellati, Brian (2018). "That's Mine! Learning Ownership Relations and Norms for Robots". In: Thirty-second AAAI conference on artificial intelligence.

# THESIS

Brawer, Jake (2023). "Fusing Symbolic and Subsymbolic Approaches for Natural and Effective Human-Robot Collaboration". PhD thesis. Yale University.

#### TECHNICAL AND SCIENTIFIC SKILLS

Programming	Python (and scientific tools), C-C++, LATEX, Git, Jekyll, Emacs, Continu-
	ous integration (with Travis), Docker
NAT / AT AT	C 114 L D 4 L NUME DOC

ML/AI Tools Scikit-learn, Pytorch, NLTK, ROS

Robots 6+ years experience with **Baxter research robot**, 3+ years experience with **UR5** 

System 8+ years of daily **Linux** experience

# **GRANTS**

March 2018 Bridging the Gap: An NSF Workshop on Conversational Agents and Human–Robot Interaction

Justine Cassell, Brian Scassellati, Jake Brawer, Michael Madaio

NSF Cyber-Human Systems (CHS), Robust Intelligence, National Robotics Initiative. Award #1829237

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Spring Intelligent Robotics

2018/2019 Teaching Assistant

Fall 2017 Object Oriented Programming

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2014/2015 Perception and Action

Teaching Assistant

SERVICE

Conference International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids; 2018)

reviews International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS; 2020)

International Conference on Human–Robot Interaction (HRI; 2017, 2018, 2019,

2020, 2021, 2022, 2023)

International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA; 2019)

Journal ACM Transactions on Human–Robot Interaction (THRI; 2019, 2020)

reviews

Students Kevin Choi (2018)

supervised Acshi Haggenmiller (2016-2017)

Sarah Widder (2017-2019) Tan Zong Xuan (2017-2018) Kayleigh Bishop (2017-2019) John Dallard (2021-2022)